{"tossups": [{"question": "In the 1940s, this man appeared on posters advocating that war workers use suggestion boxes, and he also was shown advocating the purchase of bonds alongside Lady Columbia, whom he largely replaced. This man, whose common image is based on Horatio Kitchener, says \"I want you!\" in a recruiting poster. For 10 points, name this personification of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Uncle Sam</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the 2000s, this institution underwent a controversy when its president, former Treasury Secretary Lawrence Summers, was accused of making disparaging remarks about women's intelligence. This institution, whose early presidents included Increase Mather, is now led by Civil War historian Drew Gilpin Faust. For 10 points, name this university in Massachussetts.", "answer": "<b><u>Harvard</u></b> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man focused on social productive forces, his nation\u2019s advanced culture, and the interests of the majority as his \u201cThree Represents\u201d doctrine. This man succeeded Zhao Ziyang as General Secretary after the former\u2019s dismissal by Deng Xiaoping after the Tiananmen Massacre. For 10 points, name this leader of the Chinese Communist Party during the 1990s.", "answer": "<b><u>Jiang</u></b> Zemin", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This organization was led in the mid-twentieth century by Walter White, who oversaw publication of its journal, <em>The Crisis</em>. This organization was founded out of the Niagara  Movement following the 1908 Springfield riot by people such as W.E.B. Du Bois. For 10 points, name this black civil rights group, which successfully argued the <em>Brown v. Board</em> case.", "answer": "<b><u>NAACP</u></b> [<b><u>National Association for the Advancement of Colored People</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's little-used middle names are \"Plantagenet\" and \"Schicklgruber.\"His Social Security number is 000-00-0002, and he never forgave his mother for her affair with President Taft. He looted paintings from a Nazi stronghold as part of the Flying Hellfish. For 10 points, name this employer of Waylon Smithers and very old proprietor of the Springfield Nuclear Power Plant.", "answer": "Charles Montgomery <b><u>Burns</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Much of the Roman conquest of this island was carried out under Gnaeus Julius Agricola. The mercenaries Hengist and Horsa were invited to this island by Vortigern. The Iceni were led in an uprising by their queen Boudicca on this island. Julius Caesar visited this island twice during his conquest of Gaul. For 10 points, which island experienced a fifth-century invasion by Jutes, Saxons, and Angles?", "answer": "Great <b><u>Britain</u></b> [or <b><u>Albion</u></b>; or <b><u>Britannia</u></b>; do not accept \u201cEngland\u201d]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A member of this family moved to Arkansas to become that state's first post-Reconstruction Republican governor. Another member of this family founded the University of Chicago, and another was criticized for his flippant handling of the Attica prison riot. For 10 points, what family included Standard Oil baron John and New York governor Nelson?", "answer": "<b><u>Rockefeller</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This dynasty accepted the surrender of the Kotte kingdom. The Kraak trade, begun late in this dynasty's rule, began exporting blue and white porcelain to Europe en masse. This dynasty scuttled its \"Treasure Fleet\" after sending out the expeditions of Zheng He. This dynasty fell to Manchu invaders in 1644. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty between the Yuan and Qing.", "answer": "<b><u>Ming</u></b> dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A major leader of this party defected to become the Republican governor of Massachussetts; that was Nathaniel Banks. This party often rioted against Catholics, including burning down a church in Maine, and it nominated Millard Fillmore for President in 1856. For 10 points, name this anti-immigrant party which briefly arose prior to the Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>Know-Nothing</u></b> Party [or <b><u>American</u></b> Party]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Albania and Kosovo are the only European countries where a majority practices this religion. The Danish <em>Jyllands-Posten</em> caused an uproar in 2005 when it printed cartoons critical of an important figure in this religion. A 2009 Swiss referendum banned the construction of its minarets. For 10 points, name this religion whose followers read the Koran.", "answer": "<b><u>Islam</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 8 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This organization was targeted in November 2014 by the hashtag \"Things That Are Not Mosques\" after it erroneously identified Westminster Cathedral as a mosque. This organization, which is represented in polling maps by the color purple, is led by former metal commodities trader Nigel Farage. For 10 points, name this right-wing party that is surging in the U.K.", "answer": "<b><u>UKIP</u></b> [or <b><u>U</u></b>nited <b><u>K</u></b>ingdom <b><u>Independence Party</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man first calculated the angular radius of a rainbow using Snell's Law. This man, who believed that the pineal gland joined the body to the soul, first used two axes to display four quadrants, creating his namesake coordinate plane. For 10 points, name this mathematician and philosopher whostated \"cogito ergo sum\" or \"I think therefore I am.\"", "answer": "Rene <b><u>Descartes</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "In ths play, Fluellen ironically notes that Alexander the Great killed his best friend Cleitus (CLEE-tuss) the Black. This play's prologue asks for a \"muse of fire,\" and the St. Crispin's Day speech from this play praises \"We happy few, we band of brothers.\" For 10 points, name this Shakespeare play which depicts the title king's victory at the Battle of Agincourt (AA-jin-core).", "answer": "<em><b><u>Henry V</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "The oldest event of this type in the U.S. takes place in Mobile, Alabama and is organized by groups such as the Mystic Stripers. Another of these events is organized by \"krewes\" (crews) who travel down St. Charles Avenue and Canal Street to avoid obstructions to floats in the French Quarter. For 10 points, name this day on which pre-Lent Carnival parades take place.", "answer": "<b><u>Mardi Gras</u></b> parades", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A well-regarded American example of this genre is Douglas Moore's <em>The Ballad of Baby Doe</em>. Samuel Barber worked in this genre to create <em>Vanessa</em>, for which another composer wrote the lost <em>The Guest of Honor</em>. For 10 points, name this musical genre of Scott Joplin's <em>Treemonisha,</em> John Adams's <em>Nixon in China</em>, and George Gershwin's <em>Porgy and Bess</em>", "answer": "American <b><u>opera</u></b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In response to Joseph Stalin's order to oppose this bill, Pete Seeger released the song \"Plow Under.\" This bill, which expanded on the \"destroyers for bases\" program, was likened to giving a hose to a neighbor whose house is burning down. For 10 points, name this bill that instituted a nine-month period of supplying the Allies before the U.S. entered World War II.", "answer": "<b><u>Lend-Lease</u></b> Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Popular names for this event include an Gorta Mor and the Black 47. The simultaneous export of grain and meat products have labelled some historians to claim it was a genocide. This event was caused by an organism called phytophthora infestans or late blight. For 10 points, name this late 1840s event in which widespread crop failures caused mass starvation on a British island.", "answer": "<b><u>Irish Potato Famine</u></b> [or <b><u>Great Famine</u></b>; or an <b><u>Gorta Mor</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman hosted the reality show <em>Mr. Personality</em> and wrote the 2014 article \"Shame and Survival,\" which continues her criticism of her depiction in the book <em>My Life</em>. This employee of the Office of Legislative Affairs was secretly taped by Linda Tripp, who referred her to Kenneth Starr. For 10 points, identify this namesake of a sex scandal in the Clinton administration.", "answer": "Monica <b><u>Lewinsky</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man refuted the</u> </b><em><b><u>Patriarcha</u> </b></em><b><u>of Robert Filmer in a close reading whose sequel</u></b> <b><u>introduced the concept of \"mixing labor\" with land to create property. This man's (+)</u></b> <em><b>Some Thoughts Concerning Education </b></em><b>expanded on his concept of the mind as a (*)</b> \"tabula rasa\" or \"blank state.\" He wrote slavery into the constitution of the Carolinas. For 10 points, name this author of <em>Two Treatises on Government</em> which advocated a positive, non-Hobbesian notion of the social contract.", "answer": "John <b><u>Locke</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>Apart from Morehead State, one team from this state has won the Ohio Valley</u></b>  <b><u>Conference 23 times. The most successful team from this state has the most wins in college</u></b> <b><u>basketball history. Two teams in this state met in the Final Four of the (+)</u> 2012 NCAA Tournament, and the winning team was led by players such as Michael (*)</b> Kidd-Gilchrist and Anthony Davis. For 10 points, name this state whose two most successful college basketball teams are led by John Calipari and Rick Pitino, who has coached at Louisville since 2001.", "answer": "<b><u>Kentucky</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1987, this agent was found in the preserved body of Robert Rayford, who had died in</u></b> <b><u>St. Louis in 1969. In 1983, this agent was independently discovered by Robert Gallo and (+)</u></b> <b>Luc Montagnier, who were investigating a disease then known as GRIDS. Gaetan Dugas is sometimes called the (*)</b> \"Patient Zero\" of this virus in the United States. For 10 points, name this retrovirus discovered in 1983 to be the cause of AIDS.", "answer": "<b><u>HIV</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>While this artist was staying with Mabel Dodge Luhan, a visit to the D.H. Lawrence</u></b> <b><u>Ranch inspired her oil painting</u> </b><em><b><u>The Lawrence Tree</u></b></em><b><u>. After 1946, this artist incorporated her</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Abiquiu home into her paintings. In 1916, her future husband Alfred (*) </b>Stieglitz began displaying her paintings in his 291 gallery. For 10 points, name this woman whose depictions of the American Southwest are located in her namesake museum in Santa Fe.", "answer": "Georgia <b><u>O\u2019Keeffe</u></b> [Georgia Totto <b><u>O\u2019Keeffe</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This family abolished the post of Gonfaloniere of Justice. An early member of this family</u></b> <b><u>helped suppress the revolt of wool-carders called Ciompi. Two members of this family were</u></b> <b><u>attacked at High Mass during the (+)</u> Pazzi Conspiracy. A member of this family, Piero the Unfortunate, lost power to a friar who held the (*)</b> \"bonfire of the vanities,\" Domenico Savonarola. For 10 points, name this family headed by Cosimo and Lorenzo, which ruled Florence.", "answer": "House of <b><u>Medici</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A society along this non-European river made seals showing a seated horned god</u></b> <b><u>surrounded by animals and a bitumen-lined Great Bath. Sites along this river include the</u></b> <b><u>early port of (+)</u> Lothal, a site whose name means \"mound of death,\" Mohenjo-Daro, and the mudbrick city of (*) </b>Harappa, built around 2000 BCE before Aryan peoples arrived in the area. Alexander the Great turned back shortly after crossing, for 10 points, what river that flows south through Pakistan?", "answer": "<b><u>Indus</u></b> river [accept <b><u>Indus</u></b> Valley civilization]", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>David Harris's Omega organization advocated this activity. A Phil Ochs song about</u></b> <b><u>doing this listed flat feet and a ruptured spleen as ways to accomplish it. Nearly all people</u></b> <b><u>who did this were pardoned by Jimmy Carter, though accusations of doing it have since</u></b> <b><u>haunted (+)</u> Bill Clinton, George W. Bush, and Dick Cheney. Many people who did this temporarily (*)</b> fled to Canada. For 10 points, what was this activity which people who did not wish to fight in Vietnam performed?", "answer": "Vietnam \"<b><u>draft dodging</u></b>\" [or non-derogatory equivalents such as <b><u>evading</u></b> the Vietnam <b><u>draft</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>King Charles XII of Sweden planned to adopt this system over a period of forty years</u></b> <b><u>from 1700 to 1740, but gave up in 1711. The adoption of this system in England in 1750</u></b> <b><u>apocryphally caused rioters to chant \u201cGive us our (+)</u> eleven days.\u201d The major change of this system over its predecessor is its treatment of (*)</b> years divisible by 400. For 10 points, name this calendar system which replaced the Julian Calendar and which is named for the Pope who introduced it in 1582.", "answer": "<b><u>Gregorian</u></b> calendar  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 8 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>The publication of newspapers inside these places was the subject of the</u> </b><em><b><u>Hazelwood v.</u></b></em>  <em><b><u>Kuhlmeier</u> </b></em><b><u>Supreme Court case. An earlier Supreme Court case about these places arose</u></b> <b><u>from a black (+)</u> armband worn to protest the Vietnam War and affirmed free speech rights in these places; that was (*)</b><em>Tinker v. Des Moines</em>. For 10 points, identify these places in which <em>Engel v. Vitale</em> invalidated prayers led by teachers.  ANSWER: public <b><u>school</u></b><u>s</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}